Ankit Kumar

+91 8757170724 • ank.ak2635@gmail.com • https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankit2635/ • https://ankak2635.github.io/#/

Summary

A data scientist experienced in building and deploying data-intensive applications. Proficient in working with machine learning, deep learning algorithms and LLMs across diverse problems.

Skills

 $Python \cdot R \cdot SQL \cdot Tableau \cdot MS \ Excel \cdot Power \ BI \cdot Data \ Visualization \cdot Machine \ Learning \cdot Deep \ Learning \cdot Natural \ Language \ Processing / NLP \cdot Feature \ Engineering \cdot Web \ Scrapping \cdot Statistics \cdot Econometrics \cdot Git \cdot Matplotlib \cdot Scikit-learn \cdot PyTorch \cdot Hugging \ Face \cdot NLTK \cdot Computer \ Vision \cdot CNN \cdot LLMs \cdot Flask \cdot AWS \cdot Streamlit$

Experience

Thomson Reuters Bengaluru

Correspondent: North America Resources

07/2022 - 07/2023

- Monitored North American resources (oil, gold, other metals) stocks.
- Writing sector specific news : deals, earnings, production and many more.
- Researching and writing about any news that moved sector's stocks.

J-PAL South Asia Bengaluru

Data Analyst (Intern) 06/2022 - 07/2022

- · Cleaned, transformed and analyzed raw primary survey data for a research on behavioural nudges.
- · Led and mentored a team of college juniors; created analysis road-map.
- · Constructed sub-group wise Nutritional Deficiency Index from the data.

Sri Satya Sai Annapoorna Trust

Bengaluru

Application Developer (Intern)

05/2021 - 06/2021

- · Created applications on Zoho Creator.
- Developed the premature version of Employee Attendance application.
- $\bullet \quad \text{I proposed and embedded a Leave Tracker application within the Employee Attendance application.} \\$

Projects

1. Customer Churn Prediction.

A python web application to predicts whether a company's customer will churn or not.

- · Used the IBM Telco Churn dataset.
- · Compares several classification models; optimized the selcted model by hyper-parameters tuning.
- The model achieved an accuracy score and recall score of 95% and 98% respectively.
- · Created a flask application.
- · Hosted the web application on AWS Elastic Beanstalk.

2. Text Solution

A <u>streamlit application</u> built in Python to summarize, analyze sentiment and compare the semantic similarity of texts.

- · The application has three features: summarizes texts, analyzes text sentiment and compares text similarity.
- · Built the entire back-end and front-end.
- All three features use the pretrained Hugging Face transformers' NLP models via API.

3. SQL: Danny's Diner Solved Use-Case

Solved the famous Danny's Diner case study using PostgreSQL.

• Demonstrates SQL skills via implementation of basic SELECT, GROUP BY, and aggregations functions to advance JOINs, CTE, CASE, DENSE RANK and Windows function.

Powered by CV Enhancy

Education

Christ University Bengaluru

Master of Arts in Applied Economics | CGPA: **8.2** / 10 07/2020 - 05/2022

St. Xavier's College Ranchi

Bachelor of Arts in Economics | CGPA: **6.4** / 10 06/2017 - 05/2020

Achievements



Research(under review for publication)

Conducted data-intensive research to obtain insight into state-wise nutritional deficiency of India and suggested policy measures.



Conducted a session to guide fellow researchers at Christ University on data-driven research.

Powered by Enhancy